Guide to the Rice University Historical Commission records, 1975-1979 UA 281
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Rice University Historical Commission records
1975-1979
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Rice University
UA 281
15 Linear Feet (15 boxes)
Oral history interviews and research materials dating from 1975-1978 related to Fredericka Meiners' book, A History of Rice University: The Institute Years, 1907-1963, which was commissioned by the Rice Historical Commission. This collection includes original audiotapes, transcripts of selected interviews, related correspondence, documents, typescripts, and notes, and a digitized version of the audiotapes (created 2003 by the generosity of the Rice Historical Society). A small amount of office files for the Rice Historical Commission reflect the early activities and goals of the Commission during the dates 1975-1978.
Historical Sketch
The Rice Historical Commission was formed in 1975, largely due to the inspiration of alumnus Willoughby Williams (Rice '39), who worked hard to organize support for the creation of written histories of Rice. Under the Commission's direction, with H. Malcolm Lovett as chairman, historian Fredericka Meiners (Rice '63) directed the history project which resulted in the 1982 publication of A History of Rice University: The Institute Years, 1907-1963. Historian and provost Frank Vandiver and archivist Nancy Boothe assisted in this project, as did many others.
The Rice Historical Commission is currently known as the Rice Historical Society. Its mission is to collect and preserve the history of Rice University.
The Society generously provided funding for the 2003 digital preservation of the original and unique oral history interviews in this collection.
Scope and Contents
Oral history interviews and research materials dating from 1975-1978 related to Fredericka Meiners' book, A History of Rice University: The Institute Years, 1907-1963, which was commissioned by the Rice Historical Commission. This collection includes original audiotapes, transcripts of selected interviews, related correspondence, documents, typescripts, and notes, and a digitized version of the audiotapes (created 2003 by the generosity of the Rice Historical Society). A small amount of office files for the Rice Historical Commission reflect the early activities and goals of the Commission during the dates 1975-1978.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research. Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Acquisition Note
Transferred to the Woodson Research Center in 1984 and 2000.
Index Terms
Subjects
Research; Rice University -- History; Universities and colleges
Document Types
oral histories (document genres)
- Series I: Office Files, 1975-1979; 155178
  - Statement of Purpose and Proposed Budget, 1975; 155179 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Association of Rice Alumni Committee on University History, 1975-1976; 155180 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Minutes and Agendas, 1975-1977; 155181 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Member Rosters, 1975-1978; 155182 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters of Invitation List, 1976; 155183 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Grant Information Files, 1976; 155184 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Newsletters, 1976-1979; 155185 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - NSF Proposal (Not Submitted), 1977; 155186 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1975-1979; 155187 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Newsclips, 1975-1978; 155188 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Financial Statements, 1977, 1979; 155189 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Brochures, Invitation, 155190 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Series II: Interviews, 1976-1978; 155192
  General
  Oral history interviews conducted by Fredericka Meiners 1976-1978 on behalf of the Rice Historical Commission. This series includes original audiotapes, transcripts of selected interviews, related correspondence, documents, and notes, and a digitized version of the audiotapes (created 2003 by the generosity of the Rice Historical Society). These interviews form much of the basis for Meiner's book A History of Rice University: The Institute Years, 1907-1963, which was commissioned by the Rice Historical Commission.
  - Subseries A: Audiotapes of Interviews, 155193
    See notes regarding which audiotapes have transcripts and/or digital cd-rom versions of the tapes.
    - Allen, Herbert, 9/27/1977; 155196 (Box 2a)
      [transcript, box 3.1; 2 digital cd-roms box 14]
    - Batjer, Helen (2 tapes), 8/10/1976; 155197 (Box 2a)
      [transcript, box 3.2; 2 digital cd-roms box 14]
    - Battista, Joseph L., 3/8/1978; 155198 (Box 2a)
      [1 digital cd-rom box 14]
    - Bourgeois, Andre, 11/28/1977; 155251 (Box 2a)
      [2 digital cd-roms box 14]
    - Bray, Hubert E., 6/18/1976; 155252 (Box 2a)
      [transcript, box 3.6; 2 digital cd-roms box 14]
    - Bray, Hubert E., 9/30/1976; 155253 (Box 2a)
      [transcript, box 3.6; 1 digital cd-rom box 14]
    - Bulbrook, Harry M., 10/28/1977; 155254 (Box 2a)
      [transcript, box 3.8; 1 digital cd-rom box 14]
    - Burka, Paul, 9/12/1978; 155255 (Box 2a)
    - Camden, Carroll, 9/20/1977; 155256 (Box 2a)
      [transcript, box 3.10; 1 digital cd-rom box 14]
    - Chapman, Allen, 9/30/1977; 155257 (Box 2a)
    - Class, Calvin M., 1/20/1978; 155258 (Box 2a)
      [transcript, box 3.12; 2 digital cd-roms box 14]
    - Cowan, Finis E., 3/16/1978; 155259 (Box 2a)
      [transcript, box 3.14; 1 digital cd-rom box 14]
    - Davis, Joe W., 2/21/1978; 155260 (Box 2a)
    - Dwyer, C.A., 7/26/1977; 155261 (Box 2a)
      [transcript, box 3.16; 1 digital cd-rom box 14]
    - Emison, Sam & Mary Frances, 9/21/1977; 155262 (Box 2a)
    - Erfurth, August, 9/20/1977; 155263 (Box 2a)
    - Eubank, Nancy M., 2/22/1978; 155264 (Box 2a)
      [transcript, box 3.21; 2 digital cd-roms box 14]
    - Filson, Martha, 2/19/1976; 155265 (Box 2a)
      [transcript, box 3.22; 1 digital cd-rom box 14]
    - Fuermann, G. & M. Johnson, 8/5/1977; 155266 (Box 2b)
    - Fulton, James S., 9/30/1977; 155267 (Box 2b)
      [transcript, box 4.2; 2 digital cd-roms box 14]
    - Gallegly, Joseph, 10/26/1976; 155268 (Box 2b)
    - Giles, James Bernard, 9/6/1978; 155269 (Box 2b)
      [transcript, box 4.4; 2 digital cd-roms box 14]
    - Hartsook, A.J., 7/21/1977; 155270 (Box 2b)
    - Heaps, Belle, 2/17/1978; 155271 (Box 2b)
    - Hobby, William P., 7/28/1977; 155272 (Box 2b)
      [transcript, box 4.7; 1 digital cd-rom box 14]
    - Jameson, Florence, 2/3/1978; 155273 (Box 2b)
    - Kirkland, William A., 7/19/1977; 155274 (Box 2b)
    - Kotch, Clara Margaret, 2/10/1978; 155275 (Box 2b)
      [transcript, box 4.11; 2 digital cd-roms box 14]
    - Lane, Sarah, 7/1/1977; 155276 (Box 2b)
    - Lankford, Raymond, 1/30/1978; 155277 (Box 2b)
      [transcript, box 4.13; 2 digital cd-roms box 14]
    - Lovett, H. Malcolm, 5/19/1976; 155278 (Box 2b)
      [transcript, box 4.14; 2 digital cd-roms box 14]
    - Lovett, H. Malcolm, 10/18/1976; 155279 (Box 2b)
      [2 digital cd-roms box 15]
    - Lovett, H. Malcolm, 6/27/1977; 155280 (Box 2b)
      [transcript, box 4.14; 2 digital cd-roms box 15]
    - Lovett, H. Malcolm, 3/29/1978; 155281 (Box 2b)
    - McBride, Guy T., 10/24/1977; 155282 (Box 2b)
      [transcript, box 4.15; 1 digital cd-rom box 15]
    - McEnany, M.V., 9/1/1977; 155283 (Box 2b)
      [transcript, box 4.16; 1 digital cd-rom box 15]
    - Morehead, James C., 4/6/1978; 155284 (Box 2b)
      [transcript, box 4.17; 1 digital cd-rom box 15]
    - Mosle, Paula M., 9/7/1978; 155285 (Box 2c)
      [transcript, box 4.18; 2 digital cd-roms box 15]
    - Nealon, Clark, 2/2/1978; 155286 (Box 2c)
    - Neely, Jess C., 10/10/1977; 155287 (Box 2c)
      [transcript, box 4.20; 2 digital cd-roms box 15]
    - Nunn, Stayton, 4/5/1978; 155288 (Box 2c)
      [transcript, box 5.1; 2 digital cd-roms box 15]
    - Parish, John E., 9/28/1977; 155289 (Box 2c)
      [transcript, box 5.3; 2 digital cd-roms box 15]
    - Pitzer, Kenneth Sanborn, 10/26/1977; 155290 (Box 2c)
      [transcript, box 5.4; 2 digital cd-roms box 15]
    - Red, Lel, 6/28/1977; 155291 (Box 2c)
      [1 digital cd-rom box 15]
    - Reynolds, Walter M., 9/19/1977; 155292 (Box 2c)
    - Richter, G.H., 7/5/1977; 155293 (Box 2c)
    - Richter, G.H., 3/9/1978; 155294 (Box 2c)
    - Sanders, Isaac, 7/27/1976; 155295 (Box 2c)
    - Shelton, Fred V., 9/29/1977; 155296 (Box 2c)
    - Shimek, Joe & Evelyn, 9/22/1977; 155297 (Box 2c)
    - Sims, James R., 1/18/1978; 155298 (Box 2c)
    - Stancliff, Fred J., 9/28/1977; 155299 (Box 2c)
    - Teague, James U., 6/29/1077; 155300 (Box 2c)
      [transcript, box 5.14; 1 digital cd-rom box 15]
    - Thomas, Joe D., 7/13/1977; 155301 (Box 2c)
      [transcript, box 5.15; 1 digital cd-rom box 15]
    - Vandiver, Frank E., 4/3/1978; 155302 (Box 2c)
      [transcript, box 5.17; 2 digital cd-roms box 15]
    - Vandiver, Frank E., 4/25/1978; 155303 (Box 2c)
      [transcript, box 5.17; 1 digital cd-rom box 15]
    - Waples, Margaret A., 2/24/1976; 155304 (Box 2c)
  - Subseries B: Interview Files, 155305
    (transcripts where noted, correspondence, notes, deed of gift)
    - Allen, Herbert (includes transcript), 9/27/1977; 155306 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Batjer, Helen (2 tapes) (includes transcript), 8/10/1976; 155307 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Battista, Joseph L., 3/8/1978; 155308 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Bourgeois, Andre, 11/28/1977; 155309 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Bray, Hubert E. (includes transcript), 6/18/1976; 155310 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Bray, Hubert E. (includes transcript), 9/30/1976; 155311 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Brown, George R. (no tape or transcript), 155312 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Bulbrook, Harry M. (includes transcript), 10/28/1977; 155313 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Burka, Paul, 9/12/1978; 155314 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Camden, Carroll (includes transcript), 9/20/1977; 155315 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Chapman, Allen, 9/30/1977; 155316 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Class, Calvin M. (includes transcript), 1/20/1978; 155317 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Collins, Jacquelin (no tape or transcript), 155318 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Cowan, Finis E. (includes transcript), 3/16/1978; 155319 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Davis, Joe W., 2/21/1978; 155320 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Dwyer, C.A. (includes transcript), 7/26/1977; 155321 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Eikenberg, C. Virgil (no tape or transcript), 155322 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Elliston, Laura Duff (no tape or transcript), 155323 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Emison, Sam & Mary Frances, 9/21/1977; 155324 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Erfurth, August, 9/20/1977; 155325 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Eubank, Nancy M. (includes transcript), 2/22/1978; 155326 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Filson, Martha (includes transcript), 2/19/1976; 155327 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Fuermann, G. & M. Johnson, 8/5/1977; 155328 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Fulton, James S. (includes transcript), 9/30/1977; 155329 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Gallegly, Joseph, 10/26/1976; 155330 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Giles, James Bernard (includes transcript), 9/6/1978; 155331 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Hartsook, Arthur J., 7/21/1977; 155332 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Heaps, Belle, 2/17/1978; 155333 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Hobby, William P. (includes transcript), 7/28/1977; 155334 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Hudspeth, C.M. (no tape or transcript), 155335 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Jameson, Florence, 2/3/1978; 155336 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Kirkland, William A., 7/19/1977; 155337 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Kotch, Clara Margaret (includes transcript), 2/10/1978; 155338 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Lane, Sarah, 7/1/1977; 155339 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Lankford, Raymond (includes transcript), 1/30/1978; 155340 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Lovett, H. Malcolm (includes transcript), 155341 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - McBride, Guy T. (includes transcript), 10/24/1977; 155342 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - McEnany, M.V. (includes transcript), 9/1/1977; 155343 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Morehead, James C. (includes transcript), 4/6/4978; 155344 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Mosle, Paula Meredith (includes transcript), 9/7/1978; 155345 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Nealon, Clark, 2/2/1978; 155346 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Neely, Jess C. (includes transcript), 10/10/1977; 155347 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Nunn, Stayton (includes transcript), 4/5/1978; 155348 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Ossenfort, Shirley S. (no tape or transcript), 155349 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Parish, John E. (includes transcript), 9/28/1977; 155350 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Pitzer, Kenneth Sanborn (includes transcript), 10/26/1977; 155351 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Rayzor, Mrs. J. Newton (no tape or transcript), 155352 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Red, Lel, 6/28/1977; 155353 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Reynolds, Walter M., 9/19/1977; 155354 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Richter, G.H., 7/5/1977; 155355 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Sanders, Isaac, 7/27/1976; 155356 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Shelton, Fred V., 9/29/1977; 155357 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Shimek, Joe & Evelyn, 9/22/1977; 155358 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Sims, James R., 1/18/1978; 155359 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Stancliff, Fred J., 9/28/1977; 155360 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Teague, James U. (includes transcript), 6/29/1977; 155361 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Thomas, Joe D. (includes transcript), 7/13/1977; 155362 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Tillett, Henry A. (no tape or transcript), 155363 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Vandiver, Frank E. (includes transcript), 4/1978; 155377 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Waples, Margaret A., 2/24/1976; 155378 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Whitmore, Bill (no tape or transcript), 155379 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Wilson, Mrs. Harold (no tape or transcript), 155380 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Unconducted Interview Requests, 155381 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Oral Interview Materials, 155382 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Oral History Deed of Gift Forms, 155383 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Subseries C: Digital CD-Roms, 155384
    (digitized version of original audio-cassette recordings, created Fall 2003)
    - Allen, Herbert, 155385 (Box 14)
      2 digital cd-roms
    - Batjer, Helen (2 tapes), 155392 (Box 14)
    - Battista, Joseph L., 155393 (Box 14)
      1 digital cd-rom
    - Bourgeois, Andre, 155394 (Box 14)
    - Bray, Hubert E., 155395 (Box 14)
    - Bray, Hubert E., 155396 (Box 14)
    - Bulbrook, Harry M., 155397 (Box 14)
    - Burka, Paul, 155398 (Box 14)
      digital cd-roms
    - Camden, Carroll, 155399 (Box 14)
    - Chapman, Allen, 155400 (Box 14)
    - Class, Calvin M., 155401 (Box 14)
    - Cowan, Finis E., 155402 (Box 14)
    - Davis, Joe W., 155403 (Box 14)
      digital cd-rom
    - Dwyer, C.A., 155404 (Box 14)
    - Emison, Sam & Mary Frances, 155405 (Box 14)
    - Erfurth, August, 155406 (Box 14)
    - Eubank, Nancy M., 155407 (Box 14)
    - Filson, Martha, 155408 (Box 14)
    - Fuermann, G. & M. Johnson, 155409 (Box 14)
    - Fulton, James S., 155410 (Box 14)
    - Gallegly, Joseph, 155411 (Box 14)
    - Giles, James Bernard, 155412 (Box 14)
    - Hartsook, A.J., 155413 (Box 14)
    - Heaps, Belle, 155414 (Box 14)
    - Hobby, William P., 155415 (Box 14)
    - Jameson, Florence, 155416 (Box 14)
    - Kirkland, William A., 155417 (Box 14)
    - Kotch, Clara Margaret, 155418 (Box 14)
    - Lane, Sarah, 155419 (Box 14)
    - Lankford, Raymond, 155420 (Box 14)
    - Lovett, H. Malcolm, 155421 (Box 14)
    - Lovett, H. Malcolm, 155429 (Box 15)
    - Lovett, H. Malcolm, 155430 (Box 15)
    - Lovett, H. Malcolm, 155431 (Box 15)
    - McBride, Guy T., 155432 (Box 15)
    - McEnany, M.V., 155433 (Box 15)
    - Morehead, James C., 155434 (Box 15)
    - Mosle, Paula M., 155435 (Box 15)
    - Nealon, Clark, 155436 (Box 15)
    - Neely, Jess C., 155437 (Box 15)
    - Nunn, Stayton, 155438 (Box 15)
    - Parish, John E., 155439 (Box 15)
    - Pitzer, Kenneth Sanborn, 155440 (Box 15)
    - Red, Lel, 155441 (Box 15)
    - Reynolds, Walter M., 155442 (Box 15)
    - Richter, G.H., 155443 (Box 15)
    - Richter, G.H., 155444 (Box 15)
    - Sanders, Isaac, 155445 (Box 15)
    - Shelton, Fred V., 155446 (Box 15)
    - Shimek, Joe & Evelyn, 155447 (Box 15)
    - Sims, James R., 155448 (Box 15)
    - Stancliff, Fred J., 155449 (Box 15)
    - Teague, James U., 155450 (Box 15)
    - Thomas, Joe D., 155451 (Box 15)
    - Vandiver, Frank E., 155452 (Box 15)
    - Vandiver, Frank E., 155453 (Box 15)
    - Waples, Margaret A., 155454 (Box 15)
- Series III: Research Materials, 155455
  These research materials and drafts pertain to F. Meiner's A History of Rice University: The Institute Years, 1907-1963, which was commissioned by the Rice Historical Commission. (8 boxes)
  - TS-B. Pedeaux's Introduction for Writing a Rice University History, 155456 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - TS – Preliminary Draft with Revisions of F. Meiner's Book, 155457 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Card File of Professors at Rice Institute, 1916-1963 by Department, 155464 (Box 7)
  - Card File of Fellows at Rice Institute, 1916-1963 by Department, 155465 (Box 8)
  - Card File of Notes from Various Sources on University Activities from 1907-1930s, 155466 (Box 9)
  - Card File of Notes from Various Sources on University Activities from 1940s-1960s, 155476 (Box 10)
  - Card File of Bibliography, Interviews, Index (Author's Arrangement of Materials has been Retained), 155477 (Box 11)
  - Accounting Systems, 155478 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Administration, 155479 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Architecture at Rice, no. 29, 155480 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Arts Advisory Council Report, 155481 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Athletics Budget, 155482 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Board Minutes - Original Lists, 155483 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Board Minutes, 155484 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Board of Governors, 155485 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Book of the Opening, 155486 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Budgets, 1913-1934; 155487 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Budgets, 1934-1958; 155488 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - By-Laws, 155489 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Chapter V, 155490 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Committee on Student Housing, 155491 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Committees, 155492 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Construction - Original, 155493 (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1976-1978; 155494 (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - Departments, 155495 (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - Dissertation: Feld, Allen Abraham. Harry Alexander Scott: Teach, Scholar, Administrator., 155496 (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - Faculty Minutes, 155497 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Finances, 155498 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Financial Statements, 155499 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Graduate Degrees, 155500 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Lear, Floyd Seward "History and the Humanities at Rice Between Two Wars", 155501 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Lovett - Drake Correspondence, 155502 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Lovett's World Trip, 155503 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Math Department, History and Faculty, 155504 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Meiner's Research Agenda, 155505 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous, 155506 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Original Faculty, 155507 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Other University Histories, 155508 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Pamphlet, 155509 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Phi Beta Kappa, 155510 (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Presidential Search, 155511 (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - President's Papers, 155512 (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Thresher, 155513 (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - Vandiver, Frank E., 155514 (Box 13, Folder 18)
  - Wiess, Harry C., 155515 (Box 13, Folder 19)
  - Faculty Wife's Reminiscences of Early Campus Life (Mrs. Harold A. Wilson?), 155516 (Box 13, Folder 20)
  - Students' Defense of Professor Lyford Edwards, 1919, 155517 (Box 13, Folder 21)